Eastwood Lane Papers
Eastwood Lane Papers
1899-1994
Lane, Eastwood, 1879-1951.
4.0 linear ft.
Biographical material, correspondence-subject files, memorabilia, scores and writings of the New York State composer. Much of the material is undated.
2681979
Biographical History
Sidney Eastwood Lane (1879-1951), known professionally simply as Eastwood Lane, was an American composer and author from New York State. His compositions include piano suites, impressionist pieces, and ballet; perhaps his best-known piece is Adirondack Sketches.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Eastwood Lane Papers consists of biographical material, correspondence-subject files, memorabilia, scores and writings.
Biographical material includes biographical sketches, a biographical article by Norman Gentieu and notes about the Eastwood Family.
Correspondence-subject files most of which is undated, contains single letters from composers William Berwald, Charles Huerter, and Deems Taylor, contemporaries and friends of Lane. The largest group of correspondence is with soprano Modena Scovill Lane, his wife. Many of these were written from Lane's Adirondack home and discuss the natural surroundings as well as local events and news.
Memorabilia includes clippings, concert programs, photographs, promotional material for Lane's published music, modern recordings of his compositions, address books and an essay about the Adirondacks by his Aunt Ella Eastwood Wood.
Scores is by far the largest component of this collection. Some pieces are in sketch form, others in published format. Few of the handwritten scores are dated.
Writings includes diaries, notes for a play, letters to editors and articles.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence, memorabilia scores and writings are all arranged alphabetically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Music; New York State; Lane, Eastwood, 1879-1951.; Benet, William Rose, 1886-1950.; Berwald, W. (William), 1864-1948.; St. Denis, Ruth, 1880-1968.; Scovill, Modena.; Shawn, Ted, 1891-1972.; Taylor, Deems, 1885-1966.; Composers -- United States.; Composition (Music); Articles.; Audiocassettes.; Compact discs.; Correspondence.; Photographs.; Poems.; Programs (documents); Scores.; Scrapbooks.; Sketches.; Composers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Access to recordings requires advance notice to produce a use copy.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Norman Gentieu, 1982.
Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Franklin E. Dunham, 2013.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Biographical article "Eastwood Lane" by Norman Gentieu in Journal of jazz studies, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Eastwood Family history, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence subject files
  - General correspondence, 1902; 1911-1950,; undated (Box 1)
  - American Piano Company (AMPICO), 1924; 1927 (Box 1)
  - American Society of Composers, Authors and Publishers (ASCAP), 1925; 1938,; 1942 (Box 1)
  - Benét, William Rose, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Berwald, William, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Crane, Nathalia, 1929; undated (Box 1)
  - Denishawn, The Ruth St. Denis and Ted Shawn School of Dancing, 1924; 1927 (Box 1)
  - Huerter, Charles J., undated (Box 1)
  - Menth, Herma, 1911 (Box 1)
  - Scovill, Modena, 1943-1946; undated (Box 1)
  - Taylor, Deems, undated (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Clippings
    - About Eastwood lane, 1920-1937; undated (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1912-1948; undated; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Concert programs
    - Performances by Eastwood Lane, 1924 (Box 1)
    - Performances by Modena Scovill, 1919-1926 (Box 1)
    - Performances of Eastwood Lane works, 1915-1933 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1910-1930 (Box 2)
  - Photographs
    - Case, Anna, 1911 (Box 2)
    - Denishawn: Ruth St. Denis and Ted Shawn, undated (Box 2)
    - Dietrich, George, 1922 (Box 2)
    - Hollins, Alfred, undated (Box 2)
    - Kasner, Jacques, 1913 (Box 2)
    - Lane, Eastwood, undated (Box 2)
    - McMahon, Aline, 1914 (Box 2)
    - Noyes, Byron E., 1910 (Box 2)
    - Russell, Alexander, 1910 (Box 2)
    - Scovill, Modena, undated (Oversize 2)
    - Sorrentine, Umberto, undated (Box 2)
    - Taylor, Deems, 1918; 1920 (Box 2)
    - Werrenrath, Reinald, 1920 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous unidentified, undated (Oversize 2)
  - Promotional material
    - Ampico recordings of Eastwood Lane scores, undated (Box 2)
    - Fischer Editions, 1916-1929; 1942,; undated (Box 2)
    - Hinds, Hayden & Eldredge, 1915-1917; undated (Box 2)
  - Recordings
    - Piano Deco: Mike Polad plays American music of the 1920s, Eastwood Lane, Bix Biederbecke, Rube Bloom, 1994; lane_e_0001; 1 Audiocassette (Box 4)
    - Piano Deco: Mike Polad plays American music of the 1920s, Eastwood Lane, Bix Biederbecke, Rube Bloom, 1994; lane_e_0002; 1 Compact disc (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Address books and notebooks, 1918; undated (Box 3)
    - Adirondack Wildlings by Ella Eastwood Wood, undated (Box 3)
    - Assorted mementos, 1913; 1923-1926,; 1940-1943,; undated (Oversize 2)
- Scores
  - Handwritten
    - Abelard and Heloise from Pantomime, undated (Oversize 1)
    - Ann Rutledge (fragment), undated (Box 2)
    - The Blue Robed Mandarin, undated (Oversize 1)
    - Boston Fancy (sketch), undated (Oversize 1)
    - Calm Lake and Quiet Lovers from Central Park Suite, undated (Oversize 2)
    - Cande from Jesuits' Journey and Shropshire, undated (Box 2)
    - A Corporal's Ballad, undated (Oversize 1)
    - The Crap Shooter (A Negro Ballad), undated (Oversize 1)
    - The Elfin Knight words by Langdon Warner, undated (Oversize 1)
    - Fourth of July Parade (sketches), undated (Oversize 1)
    - Gay Occasion, undated (Oversize 1)
    - Gray Winds, Dream Laden words by Cathal O'Byrne, undated (Oversize 1)
    - Great White Way, undated (Oversize 1)
    - A Gringo Dance, undated (Oversize 2)
    - A Gringo Tango, undated (Oversize 2)
    - Harlem Town, undated (Oversize 1)
    - I'm in Love with a Girl from the Country, undated (Oversize 1)
    - In Sleepy Hollow, undated (Oversize 2)
    - Incidental Music to a Dream (sketches), undated (Oversize 1)
    - Jesuits' Journey, undated (Oversize 1)
    - Joanne words by Joseph Wells Singleton, undated (Oversize 2)
    - Katrina's Waltz, undated (Oversize 1)
    - Knee High to a Grasshopper, undated (Oversize 1)
    - Lady Jane Grey, undated (Oversize 2)
    - The lady of the Palankeen, undated (Box 2)
    - Lines to Ann Rutledge, undated (Oversize 1)
    - Little Boys Sail Little Boats (unfinished), undated (Oversize 1)
    - Liza: A Spring Pastoral, undated (Oversize 1)
    - Lovers by the Lake from Central Park Sketches, undated (Box 2)
    - March - Finale (sketch), undated (Box 2)
    - A Mid-October Afternoon from In Sleepy Hollow, undated (Oversize 1)
    - Minuet for Betty Schuyler from Fourth of July Suite, 1951 (Box 2)
    - Minuet to Betty Schuyler (unfinished sketch), undated (Oversize 1)
    - North of Boston, undated (Oversize 1)
    - Notebook with sketches and fragments, undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - On Tapan Zee, A Boat Song, undated (Oversize 1)
    - Overlooking Harlem (fragment), undated (Box 2)
    - Parade from Fourth of July Suite, undated (Oversize 1)
    - Persimmon Pucker, undated (Oversize 1)
    - Plymouth in Autumn, undated (Oversize 1)
    - Polonaise, undated (Box 2)
    - Prelude - Moon Section - Opening, undated (Box 2)
    - The Road to Old Japan, 1913 (Box 2)
    - Round the Hall, A Dance Hall Ditty, undated (Oversize 2)
    - Sand Shuffle, An American Dance, undated (Oversize 2)
    - Sea Burial, undated (Oversize 2)
    - Scherzo, undated (Box 2)
    - Serenade for Mme. Chiang Kai Shek, undated (Box 2)
    - Shropshire Lass, undated (Oversize 1)
    - Sold Down the River (sketches), undated (Box 2)
    - Swanee (fragment), undated (Box 2)
    - The Time of Golden Dreams, undated (Oversize 1)
    - They've Hung Bill Jones, lyrics by Frank L. Stanton, undated (Oversize 2)
    - Tune to the Moon, undated (Box 2)
    - Watch on the Village Green from Fourth of July Suite (incomplete), undated (Oversize 1)
    - Where the Whip Willer Sings, undated (Oversize 1)
    - Workbook: Sea Burial - early sketches, Persimmon Pucker, 1910 (Box 2)
    - Unidentidfied sketches and fragments, undated (Oversize 2)
  - Published
    - Songs for Piano, 1919-1920 (Oversize 1)
    - Down Stream, 1922 (Oversize 2)
    - Summer Glow, 1919 (Box 2)
  - Source material
    - Clippings, poems and artwork, undated (Box 3)
- Writings
  - Diaries, 1899-1900; 1911-1913,; 1917-1918; 7 folders
  - The Great and Glorious (notes for a play), undated (Box 3)
  - Letters to editors, 1923; 1937-1938,; undated (Box 3)
  - Musical America article, 1914 (Box 3)
  - Opera News articles, 1914-1915 (Box 3)
  - The Piano in Our Town Musicians Club Monthly, 1915 (Box 3)
  - Poems, undated (Box 3)
  - Portrait of a Pioneer: Eulogy for William J. McAleese, 1946 (Box 3)
  - Psycho-Pianism: A Contemporary Musical Fantasy Musical America, 1914 (Box 3)
  - A Troubador En Route Musical America, 1929 (Box 3)
  - Wind and Percussion, undated (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3)